בוקר טוב Boker tov everyone. So, today's דף daf is ג׳ Gimmel
and we pick up at the bottom of ב׳ עמוד ב׳ Bet
amud bet and we're in the middle of discussing about ניסן Nissan
being the ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah for kings and I actually misstated
it yesterday. The evidence that was used was for שלמה, Shlomo, because
the counting of שלמה Shlomo count that the building of the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash was on the 480th year from the time of
יציאת מצרים Yetzias Mitzrayim and the fourth year שלמה’s Shlomo reign, so
it says from יציאת מצרים, Yetzias Mitzrayim, the counting is from ניסן.
Nissan. Similarly for kings the count is from ניסן, Nissan, and since
that is talking about שלמה, Shlomo, we're going to find out that
that's in terms of the counting for Jewish kings. I think I
accidentally said it reversed yesterday. The counting for non-Jewish kings we're going
to find out today is from תשרי, Tishrei, which actually works, because
החודש הזה לכם ראש חודשים hachodesh hazeh lachem rosh chodashim and the
significance of ניסן Nissan being the beginning was like the part of
the whole חידוש chiddush of the תורה, Torah, right? Naturally, in the
natural cycle, which the calendar which is based on the year, תשרי
Tishrei would be the beginning because that would be the beginning of
the planting season, right? So, I mean for us I know fall
tends to feel like a transitional time towards the end of the
year but from an agricultural perspective, that would be the beginning and
naturally therefore תשרי Tishrei was the ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah of months
and of years and the תורה Torah came along and said, no,
you’re going to count from the month of גאולה, geulah, from the
month of redemption and ניסן Nissan is the ראש חודשים. rosh chodashim.
And here we’re finding out that for kings as well, the counting
of years, not only of months, begins from ניסן. Nissan. For the
non-Jewish kings we’ll find out it begins from תשרי. Tishrei. But now
the גמרא Gemara takes it for granted that ניסן Nissan is the
number one in terms of numbering of the months, right? The תורה
Torah doesn’t use the name of ניסן, Nissan, תשרי, Tishrei, חשוון, Cheshvan,
כסלו, Kislev, ניסן, Nissan,
אייר, Iyar, doesn't use those names, those names actually came, are non-Jewish
names, and they came from Persia, they came after, you know, after
the first חורבן בית, churban bayis, that’s why we start finding them
in עזרא, Ezra, נחמיה Nechemya and in מגילת אסתר. Megillas Esther. So,
the תורה Torah always refers to the month as החודש הראשון, hachodesh
harishon, החודש השני hachodesh hasheini and so on, but it’s clear from
the גמרא Gemara that it’s clear from the תורה Torah that both
that that numbering of החודש הראשון hachodesh harishon is from ניסן, Nissan,
right? So, like for example when we find to the coming to
bring the קרבן פסח, korban pesach, you know, in the second year,
it’s בחודש הראשון. bachodesh harishon. Okay so clearly the numbering of the
months is from ניסן. Nissan. The גמרא’s Gemara question is that we
began yesterday, how do you know that the numbering of the years
in the תורה, Torah, when it counts the years from יציאת מצרים,
Yetzias Mitzrayim, similarly follows ניסן Nissan and when ניסן Nissan comes, it’s
now incremented a year? Of course that’s the most logical thing, but
why would you count months and years differently? But as we know
that’s exactly what we do, right? For us ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
what we say, you know, 5, 7, you know, 7, 4, whatever,
we do that to increment that at תשרי, Tishrei, whereas still the
reality is that the months are, at least the way the תורה
Torah names and counts them, counted from ניסן. Nissan. So that is
the גמרא’s Gemara question which is, are we do not it's clear
that the months in the תורה Torah counted from ניסן, Nissan, are
the years counted from ניסן Nissan as well? And it tries to
prove it from the following: that you have it says that אהרן
Aharon died, you know, אהרן Aharon was מת בהור ההר, mes behor
hahar, right? So that was on month number five, right? So that
would be ניסן, Nissan, אייר, Iyar, סיון, Sivan, תמוז, Tammuz, אב, Av,
that would be אב. Av. It says בחודש החמישי. bachodesh hachamishi. And
then משה Moshe says דברים, Devarim, right?
ויואל משה באר את התורה הזאת, vayo'el Moshe be'er es hatorah hazos,
באר את התורה be'er es hatorah whatever. Okay that’s דברים, Devarim, right?
It says he does that in month
11, which is תמוז... Tammuz... אב... Av... שבט, Shevat, thank you. Okay.
So, and it says that these are all year 40. And we
know that this happened first and this happened later. So the גמרא
Gemara says, and remember תשרי Tishrei is month 7, because we all
agree that the numbering of the months goes from ניסן. Nissan. So
it says you could not have a ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah in
here, because if you were to have a ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
in here incrementing of the years, then this would be year 41.
So nothing here can be ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah for the years,
the increment for the years, so presumably, now it could still be
anywhere between 1 through 5 and it could be 12, okay, which
we’ll get to in a minute, but the next logical candidate is
number one is ניסן Nissan is ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah for kings,
for counting of the years from יציאת מצרים. Yetzias Mitzrayim. Okay so
that’s where we left off yesterday, so let’s pick up now at
the bottom of
ב׳ עמוד ב׳. Bet amud bet.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: וממאי דמעשה דאב קדים דלמא
מעשה דשבט קדים? umimai demase de'Av kadim, dima mase de'Shevat kadim? Who
told you that the story of אב, Av, אהרן Aharon dying, came
first? Maybe the story of שבט Shevat came first? Which is of
course a completely bizarre way of reading the תורה. Torah. How would
you even begin to read the תורה Torah that משה Moshe tells
over the whole story right before they enter into the land of
ישראל Israel and all of ספר דברים Sefer Devarim and then משה
Moshe dies and then somewhere between him beginning to tell over that
story six months later. Later like אהרן Aharon dies which whatever. So
like I can't even begin to say how I don't know. Do
you find these funny suggestions? So it says what maybe this came
first so this was year forty and maybe ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
is year number seven. So actually went all the way around and
this was also year forty but it came second, alright? And therefore
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah would still be here, but if this came
first then by the time you get back to month five you're
still in the same year so ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is here.
But of course how anybody could imagine reading the תורה Torah that
way is beyond me. The גמרא Gemara says it's not so but
it doesn't necessarily go to the פסוקים pesukim we would most obviously
go to. Let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says דאמר
ליה דאחוך הדין משה כדאי d'amar lei d'achuch hadein Moshe k'dai that
doesn't make sense. דכתיב D'ketiv אחרי הכותו את סיחון מלך האמורי Acharei
hakoto et Sichon Melech ha'Emori right
so this is the beginning of דברים Devarim he tells it after
סיחון Sichon was conquered. וכי נח נפשיה דאהרן V'ki nach nafshai d'Aharon
and when אהרן Aharon died אכתי הוה סיחון קיים? akati havi Sichon
kai? סיחון Sichon was still alive? How do you know that? דכתיב
D'ketiv דף ג עמוד א daf gimal amud aleph וישמע הכנעני
מלך ערד Vayishma haKena'ani Melech Arad so the Canaanite king of Arad
heard you know יושב הנגב בבוא ישראל yoshev haNegev bivo Yisrael of
you know
so he heard when the Jewish people coming by and if you
look in the תורה Torah that appears right after it mentions that
אהרן Aharon dies. And right after it tells the story of אהרן's
Aharon death it says the Canaanite king of Arad heard and he
came and he attacked the Jewish people.
So we're going to basically say here's the short version of what
we're going to say that this guy was סיחון. Sichon. And since
he was סיחון Sichon so we see that after אהרן Aharon died
he turned and he came and he attacked the people so clearly
סיחון Sichon was still alive after אהרן Aharon died. So therefore since
סיחון Sichon was still alive here clearly the event of משה Moshe
had to happen next because משה Moshe was alive when סיחון Sichon
was killed. Now how do we know that this actually happened after
he died? You can't well in the תורה Torah it comes right
after. Of course coming right after this also comes after this. It
doesn't have to say it comes after we have to actually say
you know read that into that it's the story that clearly that
סיחון Sichon that אהרן Aharon had died. So let's take a look.
And use רש"י? Rashi?
Yeah exactly. Don't ask me about this. Okay. So מה שמועה שמע?
mah shmua shama? So what did this Canaanite king hear that he
came and attacked Israel? שמע שמת אהרן shama shemet Aharon he heard
that אהרן Aharon had died ונסתלקו ענני הכבוד v'nistalku ananei hakavod and
as a result the heavenly clouds departed and therefore the people were
vulnerable. So therefore it's not just that it's juxtaposed to the story
of אהרן Aharon dying but it reads into it that the reason
he came was because אהרן Aharon died which makes it clear that
אהרן Aharon was dead when he attacked. Now וקסבר v'kasavar once he
saw that the clouds had departed he assumed ניתנה רשות להילחם בישראל
nitna reshu lalechem b'Yisrael there's permission now to attack them they're now
vulnerable or maybe it's possible to attack them. והיינו דכתיב V'hainu d'ketiv
and that could be read into the verse ויראו כל העדה כי
גוע אהרן Vayir'u kol ha'eda ki gava Aharon right and the whole
people saw that אהרן Aharon had died which occurs right before the
attack of the king of Arad. So what does it mean they
saw that he had died? דאמר רבי אבהו D'amar Rabbi Abbahu אל
תקרי ויראו אלא וייראו al tikri vayir'u ela vayeira'u they
were made visible. Okay they had become exposed because אהרן Aharon had
died. Okay. That's more metaphorical than actually
thinking they were visible.
Yes correct. So now we have this whole דרש drash that they
became exposed and that's why he attacked. So clearly this event which
really in the תורה Torah is כנעני מלך ערד Kena'ani Melech Arad
okay which we have yet to say is going to be סיחון
Sichon we have yet to say that that event through דרש drash
not just juxtaposition came after אהרן Aharon died. And therefore since משה
Moshe was alive when סיחון Sichon was conquered he was part of
that whole war therefore clearly this event happened like the normal sequence
in the תורה Torah as well.
They became exposed or they became scared?
I think it's reading it that they became exposed from that they
their source of
protection was gone so they became fearful.
Yeah I think it's reading it exposed. Okay. If you look at
רש"י Rashi רש"י Rashi says כי גוע נתינת טעם הוא לדבר שלפניו
ki gava netinat ta'am hu ladevar shelefanav נתגלו העדה לפי שגוע אהרן.
nitgalu ha'eda lefi shegava Aharon. So נתגלו העדה nitgalu ha'eda וייראו vayeira'u
they became exposed. How does the English translate it? Exposed. Exposed yeah.
רש"י Rashi before that says exposed.
Right. נתגלו Nitgalu thank you one word in the previous רש"י Rashi
right. Okay. So ודאמר רבי אבהו v'd'amar Rabbi Abbahu אל תקרי ויראו
אלא וייראו. al tikri vayir'u ela vayeira'u. כדריש לקיש K'deResh Lakish now
דאמר ריש לקיש d'amar Resh Lakish כי ki משמש בארבע לשונות. meshamesh
b'arba leshonot. The word כי ki has four possible uses: אי, דילמא,
אלא, דהא I, dilma, ela, d'ha if, lest, rather, and because. So
meaning well I'll unpack that in a minute but meaning it's reading
it rather than ויראו כל העדה כי גוע אהרן vayir'u kol ha'eda
ki gava Aharon the people saw that אהרן Aharon had died which
is the normal way of reading כי ki as that it's reading
it that they were exposed because אהרן Aharon had died. אהרן's Aharon
death led was the source of their being exposed and that's how
it's reading. Now what is this four ways in which כי ki
functions? Actually it's more than four but So okay, אי, ei, דילמא,
dilma, אלא, ella, דהא, de-ha, okay, which now, אי ei means if,
okay, so if is the most common one, right?
רש״י Rashi has the whole list. כי תפגע שור אויבך, Ki tifga
shor oyevcha, כי יקרא קן ציפור לפניך, ki yikarei kan tzipor lefanecha,
כי תכלה, ki tichleh, כי תשא, ki tissa, right? Or כי תשא
ki tissa actually means when, okay, but we'll get to that. Okay,
but let's just say that's אי, ei, if. כי תפגע שור אויבך,
Ki tifga shor oyevcha, whatever. Okay. דילמא dilma is lest, okay. Lest
is different. Lest is if this might happen but it shouldn't happen
and therefore so for example the example of lest as רש״י Rashi
would
say is what does רש״י Rashi say? כי תאמר בלבבך, Ki tomar
bilvavcha, right? כי תאמר בלבבך רבים הגויים האלה ממני, Ki tomar bilvavcha
rabbim ha-goyim ha-eleh mimenni, right?
לא תירא מהם. Lo tira mehem. So רש״י Rashi says that not
only does the point of כי ki mean you shouldn't say it,
it means lest. Lest means not just if. Meaning they're going from
if to lest, meaning we don't
want you,
yes, but more than we don't want you to say it, it
also means it's not conditional. If it were conditional, it means if
you say in your heart that how can I conquer those nations,
then you shouldn't fear them, but if you don't say it, then
you should fear them, which isn't true, right? So if is conditional,
lest isn't conditional. Lest is you might say this, it might this
might happen, it shouldn't, and there's no aspect of the conditional. Okay,
lest you say. That's lest. אלא. ella. Now there's a great רש״י,
Rashi, רש״י Rashi brings אלא, ella, דהא de-ha in one פסוק. pasuk.
It says
ותאמר לא צחקתי Vatomer lo tzhakti by Sarah, כי יראה, ki yarei-ah,
ויאמר לא כי צחקת. Vayomer lo ki tzhakt. Okay, because rather, no,
I'm sorry, I got it reversed, I got it reversed. ותאמר
לא צחקתי כי יראה,
Vatomer lo tzhakti ki
yarei-ah, right? She said I did not laugh because she was
afraid. ויאמר לא כי צחקת, Vayomer lo ki tzhakt, no, rather you
did laugh. Rather. Okay. Okay. So those are four different ways כי
ki functions. Now actually there are more than just the four, okay?
There is also the issue of when, okay? So רש״י Rashi says
when is כאשר, ka'asher, which is like the example רש״י Rashi has
of כאשר ka'asher is כי תשא, ki tissa, right? כי תשא את
ראש בני ישראל Ki tissa et rosh benei Yisrael is when. So
רש״י Rashi sort of says that which is כאשר, ka'asher, so רש״י
Rashi sort of says that כי ki there, which is when, which
is כאשר, ka'asher, he could have said that that fits into אי
ei because sometimes we have אם im which means when, like אם
כסף תלוה את עמי Im kesef talveh et ammi which חז״ל Chazal
say, you know, they say what does it really mean, it's an
option? It means so it sort of means like when. So sometimes
that's a little bit of a stretch, but sometimes we have אי
ei to mean when, so we say אי ei includes both if
and when. So we sort of get that in there as well.
Okay. The problem is, so anyway, כי ki is a pretty pretty
multi-functional word. The funny thing is is that the simple thing, the
simple use of the word אם, im, of כי ki in this
פסוק pasuk is not one of these four things. Because the simple
use of the פסוק pasuk is ויראו כל העדה כי גוע אהרן
Vayiru kol ha-edah ki gava Aharon means that. That was not one
of those four options, right? So רש״י Rashi actually says that the
that sort of fits in, where does the that fit in?
Wait a minute, תוספות Tosafot says
it. Where is this? Hold on.
Oh, he says that that means when. He says that the פשט
pshat is the rather than that, which I would really say the
פשט, pshat, he wants to say that the other, the way we
would have read it is all the nations saw when אהרן Aharon
died. Although it's pretty funny because I think that the פשט pshat
is כי ki is a that, which is not one of those
top four.
Okay, so where does when go in there?
When רש״י Rashi places under אם. im. Since אם im sometimes means
when, yeah, yeah, תוספות Tosafot and רש״י Rashi both agree to that.
But the problem is that the simple sense of a that, which
is פשט pshat of the כי ki in the פסוק, pasuk, is
not there. Okay, anyway, back to the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. מי דמי,
mi dami, says the גמרא, Gemara, how can you compare it? התם
כנען הכא סיחון. hatam Kena'an hacha Sichon. Okay, very nice, but that
was כנען, Kena'an, you're trying to prove something about when סיחון Sichon
was alive.
תנא ברייתא, tana baraita, who סיחון, Sichon, who ערד, Arad, who כנען?
Kena'an? He was סיחון, Sichon, he was ערד, Arad, he was
כנען. Kena'an. סיחון שדומה לעייר במדבר, Sichon she-domeh le-ayyar ba-midbar, סיחון Sichon
because he was like a wild colt in the desert. כנען על
שם מלכותו, Kena'an al shem malchuto, כנען Kena'an was his kingdom. ומה
שמו, u-mah shemo, what was the name? ערד שמו, Arad shemo, that
was his personal name. So actually he was actually the king of
סיחון, Sichon, who was king of the Amorite, אמורי, Amori, was also
a king of the כנען Kena'an people.
I know it's כנען על
שם מלכותו.
Kena'an
al shem malchuto.
Well, because what? I know, it says, I think it's
תוספות, Tosafot, I think it's תוספות Tosafot says it. I think it's
claiming that he was the king of both, like he had but...
right. So it's very funny. Now תוספות Tosafot quotes an interesting מדרש
Midrash which says that he dressed up, it was סיחון Sichon dressing
up as a Canaanite king.
Okay, so maybe because he wanted to, I don't know, make that
they would pray that God should save them from the Canaanites and
he wasn't a Canaanite, he was סיחון, Sichon, so therefore, okay, and
he was an Amorite. Anyway, okay, so let's keep on going. גמרא
Gemara says like this: ומה שמו סיחון שמו. U'mashmo Sichon shmo. ואיכא
דאמרי, V'eikah d'amrei, others say ערד שדומה לערוד במדבר, Arad shedomah l'arohd
b'midbar, he was like a wild ass in the desert, כנען שם
מלכותו, Knaan shem malchuto, כנען Knaan was his
kingship, and again כנען Knaan and Amorite you have to say, ומה
שמו סיחון שמו. U'mashmo Sichon shmo. Okay, fine. Anyway, somehow we went
to a lot of effort to explain something which should have been
פשוט פשט. pashut peshat. But now what we've done is we've got
this in the right sequence, so ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah cannot happen
anywhere between five and eleven. Okay, cannot be six through eleven. So
the גמרא Gemara says, okay, but we're not done, says the גמרא,
Gemara, ואימא ראש השנה אייר, V'eima Rosh Hashanah Iyar, maybe it is,
just because you proved that it's not this, maybe it's אייר, Iyar,
maybe it's number two, okay? Right?
Who says it's ניסן? Nissan? ואימא אייר? V'eima Iyar? גמרא Gemara says,
לא סלקא דעתך, Lo salka daatach, that doesn't make sense, דכתיב ויהי
בחודש הראשון בשנה השנית באחד לחודש הוקם המשכן, Dechtiv v'hi bachodesh harishon
bashanah hashenit b'echad lachodesh hukam hamishkan, okay, so on ניסן Nissan on
year two, the משכן Mishkan was erected.
דכתיב ויהי בשנה השנית בחודש השני, Dechtiv v'hi bashanah hashenit bachodesh hasheni,
so again it's ניסן, Nissan, it's year two and now it's אייר,
Iyar, נעלה הענן מעל משכן העדות, Naalah heanan me'al mishkan haedut, okay,
so the cloud departed from the משכן. Mishkan. So if the משכן
Mishkan was erected in month one and the cloud departed month two,
month two can obviously not be ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah because then
it would be a year later, it was the... the number of
the year would be later. מדקאי בניסן וקרי שנה שנית, Midekai b'Nissan
v'karei shanah shenit, it was in ניסן Nissan and it was called
the second year, וקאי באייר, v'kai b'Iyar, and then
it was אייר Iyar when the cloud departed, וקרי שנה שניה, v'karei
shanah shenia, and it was called the second year, מכלל דראש השנה
לאו אייר הוא, Michlal d'Rosh Hashanah lav Iyar hu, obviously it's not
אייר Iyar because then it would have been called the third year,
not the second year. Okay. ואימא ראש השנה סיון? V'eima Rosh Hashanah
Sivan? We're not giving up. Okay, it can't be אייר. Iyar. Maybe
it's סיון? Sivan? Okay, maybe here, these are all within the same
year, come סיון Sivan it's one year later. ואימא סיון? V'eima Sivan?
גמרא Gemara says, לא סלקא דעתך, Lo salka daatach, that doesn't make
sense, דכתיב בחודש השלישי לצאת בני ישראל מארץ מצרים, Dechtiv bachodesh hashlishi
l'tzet Bnei Yisrael m'Eretz Mitzrayim, and the third month when the בני
ישראל Bnei Yisrael left Egypt. ואם איתא בחודש השלישי בשנה השנית לצאת
בני ישראל מארץ מצרים, V'im itah bachodesh hashlishi bashanah hashenit l'tzet Bnei
Yisrael m'Eretz Mitzrayim, right? So here we are, we're talking about מתן
תורה, Matan Torah, and so obviously they've just left Egypt. So if
the years are going to be incremented at month number three, it
should say at year two on month number three. So clearly the
year has not yet been incremented yet just because you got to
month three.
מבעי ליה. Miba'ileh. ואימא תמוז? V'eima Tammuz? We're not done. So we
still have תמוז. Tammuz. Okay. ואימא תמוז? V'eima Tammuz? ואימא אב? V'eima
Av? Right? Because here all we know is that it's not between
five and eleven. Maybe it is five? Okay, so maybe ואימא v'eima
and the last one is of course אדר, Adar, right? Is that
right?
אדר, Adar, I'm sorry, ואימא אדר, v'eima Adar, right? So these are
the three remaining possibilities.
גמרא Gemara says, ואימא אב ואימא אדר, V'eima Av v'eima Adar, אלא
אמר רבי אליעזר מהכא, Ella amar Rabbi Eliezer meihacha, ויחל לבנות בחודש
השני בשני בשנת ארבע למלכותו, Vaychal livnot bachodesh hasheni b'sheni b'shnat arba
l'malchuto, back to שלמה. Shlomo. He began to build the Temple in
the second month on the second in the fourth year of his
kingship. מאי שני? Mai sheni? What does it mean second? לאו שני
לירח שמנו בו למלכותו? Lav sheni l'yerach shemonim bo l'malchuto? It must
be the second month counting from the normal counting of months from
ניסן. Nissan. Not only that, it's also the second month of this
year of his kingship. Okay, so you get it? The first בחודש
השני, bachodesh hasheni, they didn't have names of months. בחודש השני Bachodesh
hasheni was the way of saying אייר. Iyar. Okay, and then it
says in the second in the fourth year. So what does the
second mean? It means it was אייר, Iyar, month two, year four
of his kingship. Okay, so you see that...
does this mean the second day of אייר? Iyar?
The גמרא Gemara is going to say that and reject that.
Okay? The second of the month. Since it says two and it's
not going to say... it does not mean the day, it must
again mean month. So why does it say month? The גמרא Gemara
says חודש השני chodesh hasheni to tell you that this is the
second month from when you incremented the year, that you count the
years from ניסן Nissan as well. So the גמרא Gemara says, מתקיף
לה רבינא, Matkif la Ravina, רבינא Ravina asked, ואימא שני בחודש, v'eima
sheni bachodesh, maybe it means the second of the month? No. אם
כן שני בחודש בהדיא כתיב ביה. In ken sheni bachodesh b'hedya ketiv
beh. Whenever the Torah wants to say which day of the month,
it says בחודש, bachodesh, right, בעשור בחודש, b'asor bachodesh, right, you know.
know, בחמישה לחודש, b'chamisha lachodesh,
so when it just said בשני, basheini, and what it said, right,
בשני, basheini, בשני בחודש, basheini bachodesh, ואימא
בשני בשבת?
ve'eima basheini
bashabbos? So maybe it means Monday. חדא chada number one, no. דלא
אשכחן שני בשבת דכתיב, d'lo ashckan sheini bashabbos d'chsiv, which is actually
quite fascinating, right? Go look through the entire תנ"ך Tanach and look
where it ever mentions what day of the week something occurred, right?
The only time it tells you is in בריאת העולם, bri'as ha'olam,
but you know, יום ראשון, yom rishon, יום שני, yom sheini, יום
שלישי, yom shelishi, other than that it never tells you what day
of the week anything occurred. No. No, it never, never, never, never,
never...
What about the guy carrying, collecting wood on שבת? Shabbos? Is that
what you're saying?
Yeah, other than saying it was שבת, Shabbos,
but not what day of the month.
Yeah.
ביום השישי, b'yom hashishi, it says, right. Yeah, yeah, yeah. ויהי ביום
השישי. vayehi b'yom hashishi. Other than... okay, fine. Other than Friday and
שבת. Shabbos. Other than Friday and שבת, Shabbos, those are the only
days in the תנ"ך Tanach that matter, ערב שבת... erev Shabbos...
that's pertinent to the story here and we have the day... what's
the difference if it's Monday or Tuesday?
Right. Right. So and we never find, you know, Monday
labeled. דסיפא, d'seifa, oh, מקיש שני בתרא לשני קמא, makish sheini basra
l'sheini kamma, the second בשני basheini is linked to the first בשני.
basheini. מה שני קמא חודש, mah sheini kamma chodesh, the same way
the first one was clearly the second month, אף שני בתרא חודש,
af sheini basra chodesh, the second month, but the second month to
what? Must be the second month from the beginning of the next
king's year. Okay, so in the end we get it from שלמה
Shlomo again.
So there's a ברייתא braisa in that פסוק pasuk that teaches us
when you count...
yeah, and it's not trying to teach us, it's not like there's
an extra ו vav in the פסוק pasuk to teach us, just
saying it's a way of numbering. It was אייר, Iyar,
month, you know, year four, month two of king שלמה. Shlomo. So
it's interesting, it's year four, month two of king שלמה, Shlomo, clearly
you're counting the months, you're counting the year of the kingship from
ניסן. Nissan. Okay. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says תניא כוותיה. tanya k'vosei.
Okay, so תניא כוותיה דרבי יוחנן. tanya k'vosei d'Rabbi Yochanan. We taught
like רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. מניין שאין מונים להם למלכים אלא מניסן?
minayin she'ein monim lahem l'mlachim ella miNissan? How do you know you
count from ניסן? Nissan? שנאמר, shene'emar, ויהי בשמונים שנה וארבע מאות שנה
לצאת בני ישראל מארץ מצרים. vayehi bishmonim shana v'arba me'os shana l'tzeis
b'nei Yisrael me'eretz Mitzrayim. And this, and then it mentions שלמה's Shlomo
kingship and compares it to יציאת מצרים. Yetzias Mitzrayim. וכתיב, uch'siv, ויעל
אהרן הכהן אל הר ההר על פי ה'. vaya'al Aharon hakohen el
Hor Hahar al pi Hashem. וכתיב, uch'siv, ויהי בארבעים שנה בעשתי עשר
חודש. vayehi b'arbaim shana b'ashti asar chodesh. So that shows that it
isn't תשרי. Tishrei. וכתיב, uch'siv, and then basically just write out all
the same questions the גמרא Gemara did because it was a ברייתא
braisa that listed all the פסוקים. psukim. וכתיב, uch'siv, אחרי הכותו את
סיחון. acharei hakoso es Sichon. So then it had a proof that
the events of חומש דברים Chumash Devarim happened after אהרן Aharon died.
ויאמר וישמע הכנעני. vayoimer vayishma hakena'ani. ויאמרו ויראו כל העדה כי גוע
אהרן. vayoimer vayiru kol ha'eidah ki gava Aharon. Okay. ויאמר, vayoimer, and
essentially just found out that that really doesn't prove it because it
doesn't eliminate all the other
months. ויהי בחודש הראשון בשנה השנית. vayehi bachodesh harishon bashana hashaynis. I'm
sorry, בחודש הראשון בשנה... bachodesh harishon bashana... I'm sorry, that was proving
month by month. The first few are eliminating אייר, Iyar, the contender.
ויאמר ויהי בשנה השנית בחודש השני. vayoimer vayehi bashana hasheinis bachodesh hasheini.
ויאמר בחודש השלישי לצאת בני ישראל ממצרים. vayoimer bachodesh hashlishi l'tzeis b'nei
Yisrael miMitzrayim. So
that eliminates סיון Sivan as a contender. ויאמר ויחל לבנות. vayoimer vayachel
livnos. And then finally we could eliminate all the other months so
we had to go back to the פסוק pasuk by שלמה. Shlomo.
Okay, so there's a ברייתא braisa that lists all those פסוקים. psukim.
Just point it out.
I have no idea. But did we actually eliminate אדר? Adar?
Yes, because in the end, not individually we eliminated, we eliminated because
the פסוק pasuk by שלמה, Shlomo, the second שלמה Shlomo showed you
that the counting was the same as the counting from, you know,
from
ניסן. Nissan. אמר רב חסדא, amar Rav Chisda, said רב חסדא, Rav
Chisda, לא שנו אלא למלכי ישראל. lo shanu ella l'malchei Yisrael. This
is only by Jewish kings, which by the way we were discussing
yesterday, right, are we really creating this system or is it being
done by, what do you call it, or is it being done
by, you know, is it a secular system that we're just adhering
to? So now that we find out that this is Jewish kings,
maybe you could say, I mean again, how long did this last?
Would they do this in חשמונאים Chashmonaim times? Was this all just
a nice like sort of nostalgic evocative the way things used to
be? I mean, you know, I don't know. I mean there were
pseudo-kings sort of whatever during that period. So, so maybe, so maybe
it was during, you know, during later בית שני Bayis Sheini times,
but if we're making the system, we can make it. And therefore
the beginning we discussed exactly how you would do the counting based
on when one king died and the next king began and so
on. All that is within our closed system of Jewish kings. But
non-Jewish kings we're going to see go by תשרי. Tishrei. Yes.
First המכבים Hamakabim has an interesting chronology based not on individual kings
but on the time since standard either Alexander or Seleucus, it's not
clear.
Right, so we're going to discuss that, that the actual normal counting
that was used in monetary documents was מניין שטרות, minyan shtaros, which
I think might be the same as that. I'll have to check.
Okay, but yeah. Okay, but all this is Jewish kings. Okay, אבל
למלכי אומות העולם מתשרי מנינן. aval l'malchei umos ha'olam miTishrei mininan. When
we count for non-Jewish kings, we do it from
תשרי. Tishrei. שנאמר, shene'emar, דברי נחמיה בן חכליה. divrei Nechemia ben Chachalya.
So this is the opening of נחמיה. Nechemia. ויהי בחודש כסליו. vayehi
bachodesh Kislev. Now because we're in the book of נחמיה, Nechemia, we're
post חורבן הבית churban habayis and they're now have they been taken
to בבל Bavel and פרס Paras and so on. They have now
adopted the names of the Persian months. It's very fascinating, right, how
they could have done that. I mean how they did it, obviously,
you know, you adopt the names of the surrounding culture. How you're
allowed to do that. The whole... you know, according to many ראשונים,
rishonim, החודש הזה לכם ראש חודשים hachodesh hazeh lachem rosh chodashim doesn't
just say you start your calendar in ניסן Nissan but says... have
to count חודש הראשון, Chodesh Ha-Rishon, חודש השני, Chodesh Ha-Sheni, and so
on.
All right, so the months are Babylonian.
It's Babylonian. You brought it up.
Yeah, the Babylonian calendar is very similar to ours, it's a lunar-solar
calendar.
Right, and these names were from the Babylonian months, right? תמוז Tammuz
was a Babylonian god.
Right,
right.
Yeah, not like we have anything like that, like January or Saturn
or Thor's day, Thursday. Anyway, moving on. Okay, so,
so the פסוק Passuk says like this: Okay, ויהי
בחודש כסליו שנת עשרים, Vayehi bachodesh Kislev shnat esrim, okay, so it
was כסליו Kislev the twentieth year. Then, ויהי בחודש ניסן שנת עשרים
לארתחשסתא. Vayehi bachodesh Nissan shnat esrim l'Artachshashta.
So then it was ניסן, Nissan, then the next event is פרק
ב, perek bet, we're going to see in a minute, happened later
and it's still calling it the twentieth year. How could it call
it the twentieth year? It's ניסן! Nissan! You're supposed to increment the
years for the kings on ניסן. Nissan. It must be that for
non-Jewish kings you don't increment on ניסן. Nissan. And if you're not
incrementing on ניסן, Nissan, well our next candidate is תשרי. Tishrei. So
although we went through a lot of effort here to try to
eliminate all the other contenders, by now we're basically assuming if it's
not ניסן Nissan it's going to be תשרי, Tishrei, and we see
by the non-Jewish kings clearly this event happened later and the years
have not been incremented, clearly it's not ניסן. Nissan.
Yes, but again, are we doing this just because that's what the
secular kings did or are we deciding this is how we're going
to do secular kings, because the latter makes no sense.
Yeah, I again, the only thing that makes sense is we're just
adopting their system of counting. So but and as I said, the
ברייתא baraita we had before like exactly giving you the rules was
said in the context of ניסן, Nissan, which is fine, that could
be a system we're creating. Here presumably we're just adopting their system.
So let's take a look. מדקאי בכסליו דקרי ליה שנת עשרים, Midkai
b'Kislev d'karei leh shnat esrim, it's in כסליו Kislev and it calls
it year twenty. וקאי בניסן וקרי ליה שנת עשרים, V'kai b'Nissan v'karei
leh shnat esrim, and the later event happened in ניסן Nissan and
it was still year twenty. מכלל דראש השנה לאו ניסן הוא, Miklal
d'Rosh Hashanah lav Nissan hu, obviously ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah isn't ניסן.
Nissan. This is wonderful.
How do you know, now we know the question, that the event
in נחמיה ב Nechemya bet happened after the event in נחמיה א?
Nechemya alef?
So the גמרא Gemara says: בשלמא... B'shlama... Oh wait, there's even an
earlier question. היכי מפרשת לארתחשסתא? Heich mifartesh l'Artachshashta? אלא, Ella, so fine,
the second one said it was year
twenty of the king, it mentions specifically it was counting the year
of the king. אלא האי ממאי דלארתחשסתא? Ella hai mimai d'l'Artachshashta? דילמא
למניינא אחרינא הוא? Dilma l'minyana achrina hu? Maybe the first event that
said year twenty wasn't year twenty of the king, maybe it was
year twenty of some other counting? Who knows? The גמרא Gemara says:
אמר רב פפא Amar Rav Papa says רב פפא, Rav Papa, שנת
עשרים שנת עשרים
לגזירה שווה. shnat esrim shnat esrim l'gzeirah shavah. Don't go crazy. In
both places it says year twenty, it's the same counting, it's the
same year king. Okay, so we have the same year twenty and
ניסן Nissan it's still year twenty, not year twenty-one. So now the
גמרא Gemara asks the question we're familiar with. מה התם לארתחשסתא אף
הכא לארתחשסתא. Ma hatam l'Artachshashta af hacha l'Artachshashta. Okay. וממאי דמעשה דכסליו
קדים דילמא מעשה דניסן קדים? U'mimai d'maaseh d'Kislev kadim dilma maaseh d'Nissan
kadim? How do you know the event in נחמיה א Nechemya alef
of כסליו Kislev came first? Maybe the event of ניסן Nissan came
first and that's why the year hadn't incremented because it really although
written later came first? לא סלקא דעתך. Lo salka daitach. That doesn't
make sense. Why? דתניא, D'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא: baraita: דברים
שאמר חנני לנחמיה בכסליו, Devarim she'amar Chanani l'Nechemya b'Kislev, the things that
חנני Chanani
who was the messenger that came from the Jews that were trying
to settle the land of Israel in the second עליה, aliyah,
he came and he reported the status of the Jewish community in
the land of Israel. And he came and he told them to
נחמיה, Nechemya, and that was the opening of the book of נחמיה.
Nechemya. So he told them to נחמיה Nechemya בכסליו. b'Kislev. אמר נחמיה
למלך בניסן. Amar Nechemya l'melech b'Nissan. Thankfully we're calling him now למלך.
l'melech. נחמיה Nechemya said it to the king in ניסן. Nissan. So
basically the event of נחמיה א Nechemya alef is when he received
message of the story of the Jewish community that was resettling in
the land of Israel and the event in נחמיה ב Nechemya bet
which happened in ניסן Nissan was when he now told it over
to the king, so clearly it happened later. Now דברים, Devarim, now
we're just going to quote a lot of פסוקים, psukim, okay, and
basically it's just saying it's פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim that
נחמיה ב Nechemya bet happened after נחמיה א. Nechemya alef. Let's take
a look. דברים שאמר חנני לנחמיה בכסליו שנאמר, Devarim she'amar Chanani l'Nechemya
b'Kislev shene'emar, here's what happened in נחמיה א: Nechemya alef: דברי נחמיה
בן חכליה ויהי בחודש כסליו שנת עשרים, Divrei Nechemya ben Chachalyah vayehi
bachodesh Kislev shnat esrim, it was כסליו Kislev the year twenty, ואני
הייתי בשושן הבירה, va'ani hayiti b'Shushan habirah, I was in שושן Shushan
the capital. ויבא חנני אחד מאחי, Vayavo Chanani echad me'achai, and חנני
Chanani one of my brethren came, הוא ואנשים מיהודה, hu v'anashim mi'Yehudah,
he and other people that came from יהודה, Yehudah, ואשאלם על היהודים
הפליטה, va'esh'alem al hayehudim hapleitah, and I asked them on the remnant
of the Jews, אשר נשארו מן השבי, asher nish'aru min hashvi, that
are left over from the captivity, that were maybe never taken away
in captivity or have since been in the land, ועל ירושלים, v'al
Yerushalayim, and about ירושלים, Yerushalayim, what's the story about those people that
are there trying to rebuild the city. ויאמרו לי הנשארים Vayomeru li
hanish'arim
They said to me those remnants that are left over from captivity
they are there in the country ברעה גדולה beraa gedolah it is
great evil ובחרפה u'vcherpah and great shame וחומת ירושלים מפורצת vechomat Yerushalayim
meporetzet
and the walls of Jerusalem are breached are shattered ושעריה נצתו באש
ushe'areha nitzetu va'esh and its gates have been I'm sorry have been
burnt up by fire. Okay so he told them the sad report.
So those things אמרם נחמיה למלך בניסן amaram Nechemiah lamelech beNissan
so Nechemiah reported them to the king in Nissan שנאמר ויהי בחודש
ניסן שנת עשרים לארתחשסתא המלך shenemar vayehi bechodesh Nissan shenat esrim l'Artachshasta
hamelech so it
was now Nissan year twenty יין לפניו yayin lefanav
so I was serving wine in front of him he was the
king's wine steward ואשא את היין va'esa et hayayin I lifted up
the wine I carried the wine ואתנה למלך va'etnah lamelech and I
gave it to the king ולא הייתי רע לפניו velo hayiti ra
lefanav and I was not presumably prior ever looked bad in his
presence ויאמר לי המלך vayomer li hamelech and the king said to
me מדוע פניך רעים madua panecha ra'im why are you looking so
distraught ואתה אינך חולה ve'ata aincha choleh you're not sick אין זה
כי אם רוע לב ein ze ki im roa lev this must
be a bitterness of the heart something must be distressing you ויירא
הרבה מאוד va'ira harbeh meod I was very fearful ואומר למלך va'omar
lamelech and I said to the king המלך
לעולם יחיה hamelech l'olam yichyeh the king that's the way
you this is the way you start I think to the king
the king should live forever מדוע לא ירעו פני madua lo yerau
panai
why should my face not look distraught אשר העיר בית קברות אבותי
חרבה asher ha'ir beit kivrot avotai chreva the city where my forefathers
are buried is desolate ושעריה אכלו באש ushe'areha uchlu va'esh and
its gates have been consumed by fire ויאמר לי המלך vayomer li
hamelech and the king said to me על מה זה אתה מבקש
al mah ze ata mevakesh what is it that you ask for
ואתפלל אל אלהי השמים va'etpallel el elohei hashamayim and I sort of
made a silent I made a prayer to God presumably a quick
silent prayer to God ואומר va'omar because I'm now about to ask
for a big thing and he wanted God's help that it would
be answered ואומר למלך va'omar lamelech and I said to the king
אם על המלך טוב im al hamelech tov sounds a little bit
like a if it's fine but obviously it's the classic way of
addressing the king if it's fine with the king sire if it
pleases your grace ואם ייטב עבדך לפניך ve'im yitav avdecha lifnecha and
if I have found favor in your eyes אשר תשלחני אל יהודה
asher tishlacheni el Yehudah you shall send me to Judea אל עיר
קברות אבותי ואבננה el ir kivrot avotai v'evnenah to the city where
my forefathers are buried and I will help oversee its rebuilding ויאמר
לי המלך vayomer li hamelech
and the king said to me והשגל יושבת אצלו vehashagal yoshevet etzlo
and the shagal that was sitting next to him which we're going
to say is a concubine לגש Lagesh לגש אלגשנה Lagesh Algeshna exactly
so עד מתי יהיה
מהלכך
ad matai yihyeh
mahalachecha ומתי
תשוב umatai tashuv
how long will you go for when will you be back וייטב
לפני המלך v'yitav lifnei hamelech and I gave him an answer it
was good in his eyes וישלחני vayishlacheni and he sent me ואתנה
לו זמן ve'etnah lo zman and I gave him a time when
I would return so this is the beginning of the story of
נחמיה Nechemiah how he goes back and he oversees the returning of
the Jews to the land of Israel the rebuilding of the temple.
Anyway the basic answer is how do you know that נחמיה Nechemiah
Bet is after נחמיה Nechemiah Aleph because it's פשט pshat because it's
what the פסוקים psukim say he got the report in נחמיה Nechemiah
Aleph told it over to נחמיה Nechemiah Bet this whole page that
has like eighty percent פסוקים psukim here so and quite fascinating anyway
okay so that's how you know so clearly by kings you do
not increment at ניסן Nissan and if you don't increment by non-Jewish
kings at ניסן Nissan then presumably you do it at תשרי. Tishrei.
Okay so he got to ניסן Nissan and he got the report
in כסלו Kislev the year also wouldn't have changed right
yes but that's the point first he heard the report and that
distressed him and the king asked him and then he gave over
the
report right but in other words when he heard the report and
then he gave it to the king
he heard the report in כסלו Kislev he gave it to the
king in ניסן Nissan and it's still called year twenty
I understand but what if it were the other way around the
months it would still be the same number year
correct
what are you asking
why would it have been a different year
if it
incremented in ניסן Nissan it would have been a different the year
would have been incremented would have been the
twenty-first year assuming it was either ניסן Nissan or תשרי Tishrei right
so if there's no
increment between כסלו Kislev and ניסן Nissan it must be תשרי Tishrei
because it's not
ניסן Nissan fine תשרי Tishrei okay
okay okay fine okay so אמר ליה רב יוסף amar leh Rav
Yosef so Rav Yosef asks וביום עשרים וארבעה לחודש בשישי בשנת שתיים
לדריוש ubeyom esrim ve'arba'ah lachodesh bashishi bishnat shtayim l'Daryavesh
did he come after that I'm sorry I just lost my place
תשרי Tishrei
okay
where were we okay וביום עשרים וארבעה לחודש ubeyom esrim ve'arba'ah lachodesh
on the day twenty-fourth of the month בשישי בשנת שתיים לדריוש bashishi
bishnat shtayim l'Daryavesh did I skip a line no I didn't בשישי
בשנת שתיים לדריוש bashishi bishnat shtayim l'Daryavesh presumably in the sixth month
in the second year of דריוש Daryavesh so this is in חגי
Chaggai now we're no longer in נחמיה Nechemiah וכתיב uchktiv and it
says בשביעי bashvi'i in the seventh month okay now it doesn't say
בשנת שתיים bishnat shtayim but Rashi says from the context of the
previous פסוק pasuk it's clear we're talking about year
twenty in the twenty-first of the month so here the problem is
that in חגי Chaggai
we are talking about month six year two of דריוש Daryavesh and
then the later
Now we’ve got a problem because month seven is
תשרי, Tishrei, so we should have incremented the year. Okay, ואם איתא,
ve-im issa, if it’s true that month seven, that תשרי Tishrei is
what is where we increment for non-Jewish kings, בשביעי בשנת שלש Be-shvii
bishnat shalosh מיבעי ליה, mibayei lei, it should have said in the
seventh month in year three. אמר רבי אבהו, Amar Rabbi Abahu, כורש
מלך כשר היה. Coresh Melech Kasher haya. Now what the heck כורש
Coresh means, we’re talking about דריוש. Daryavesh. So the גמרא Gemara will
ask that. But now we are going to assume, remember we assumed
before that סיחון Sichon was ערד, Arad, or ערד Arad was סיחון,
Sichon, now we’re going to say דריוש Daryavesh was כורש. Coresh. Okay,
רש״י Rashi says actually it was a
later כורש, Coresh, obviously the original כורש Coresh got the whole beginning
of the rebuilding underway, but it was like look, we know kings
were named, I mean the English kings, a lot of kings were
named, you know, same name being reused. So רש״י Rashi claims the
גמרא Gemara is not really saying this was the original כורש, Coresh,
but it was a new—it was also named כורש, Coresh, and מלך
כשר היה, Melech Kasher haya, and he was a good guy. And
רש״י Rashi says this is actually a play on the word of
כורש Coresh and
כשר. Kasher. Okay, לפיכך, lepichach, anyway, whoever this דריוש Daryavesh was, he
was a good guy, and לפיכך מנו לו כמלכי ישראל. lepichach manu
lo kemalchei Yisrael. So they counted for him like the Jewish kings.
Now they here means again maybe in the נביאים, Nevi'im, that’s how
they were counting, you know, and does it mean that in their
secular documents or in their monetary documents they had devised a whole
new way of counting? Again, it’s pretty hard to imagine. Really? So
everybody around you has called this now year three, but because you
want to treat him like a pseudo-Jewish king, right, you know, you’re
going to call his, you’re going to still call it year two
and you’re going to have a different counting going on? No one
can really imagine that that really could work. Okay, anyway, moving on.
Now by the way, I should say that the original כורש, Coresh,
right, it says in a couple of places in, doesn’t it say
in ירמיהו Yirmiyahu in places that God says I’m going to send
כורש עבדי, Coresh avdi, right, כורש Coresh my servant, right?
So—is that—no, that’s not ירמיהו. Yirmiyahu. Where does it say that? Somewhere
it says כורש עבדי. Coresh avdi. Anyway, so the fact that he’s
conceived of as a Jewish king, although that would be the original
כורש, Coresh, is not crazy. But the fact that they’re having a
different numbering system going on does seem a little crazy. Anyway, גמרא
Gemara says like this, מתקיף לה רב יוסף, Matkif lah Rav Yosef,
so רב יוסף Rav Yosef asked: חדא, Chada, number one, אם כן
קשיא קראי אהדדי. im ken kashya kraei ahadadi. I can’t buy that
they had a different counting system for him because I got other
פסוקים pesukim that contradict that. דכתיב, Dechtiv, the פסוק pasuk says, ושיציא
ביתא דנא עד יום תלתא לירח אדר דהיא שנת שית למלכות דריוש
מלכא, v'shitzia beita dena ad yom talata leyarch Adar dehi shenat sheis
lemalkut Daryavesh malka, so the completion of this house, of the temple,
completed
until the third day of the month of אדר, Adar,
which is year six of the king דריוש Daryavesh מלכא. malka. Okay.
ודתניא, Ve-detanya, באותו זמן לשנה הבאה, ve-otos zman lashana haba'ah, that time,
at that time the next year, עלה עזרא מבבל וגלותו עמו, ala
Ezra miBavel ve-galuto imo,
then עזרא Ezra started coming back with a new major
wave of עליה aliyah at that time the following year. So this
event occurred, this sort of certain stage of completion of the house
happened in the third month—I’m sorry, it’s the third day of אדר.
Adar. It happens in אדר Adar year six.
Okay, so where’s my marker?
So אדר Adar year six
is year six is some type of a
completion of the house. Okay, then at the same time אדר Adar
year seven, עזרא Ezra goes back
with whatever completion, anyway עזרא Ezra goes back with the
new wave of
עליה aliyah here. Okay, that’s at the same time עזרא Ezra goes
back. וכתיב, Uchtiv, and the verse says, ויבוא ירושלים בחודש החמישי היא
שנת השביעית למלך. vayavo Yerushalayim bachodesh hachamishi hi shenat hashvi'it lamelech. So
they start going back in אדר Adar and they come back to
ירושלים Yerushalayim בחודש החמישי, bachodesh hachamishi, what
does that mean? It’s the year seven, month אב. Av. אב Av
in seventh year. Okay, in year seven they get to ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
Okay, so what happens between these two?
ניסן, Nisan, right? So if we are counting for דריוש Daryavesh
for like he’s a good guy, so ניסן Nisan is the new
year, this should have been year eight. Okay, so you can’t tell
me that for him we count ניסן Nisan as the new year.
Okay, ואם איתא, ve-im issa, if what you're saying is true, שנת
השמינית מיבעי ליה, shenat hashminit mibayei lei, it should be year eight.
ועוד, Ve-od, number one, number two: מי דמי? Mi dami? How can
you compare and say oh he was כורש, Coresh, he was a
good guy? התם כורש הכא דריוש. Hasam Coresh hacha Daryavesh. That
one king is called כורש, Coresh, he’s an earlier king, this king
is דריוש. Daryavesh. תניא, Tanya, we start—right—no, הוא כורש
הוא דריוש הוא ארתחששתא. hu Coresh hu Daryavesh hu Artachshashta. Okay,
so this whole
ארתחששתא Artachshashta guy that we had earlier is also דריוש Daryavesh and
also כורש. Coresh. Now again רש״י Rashi says not the same כורש,
Coresh, a new כורש, Coresh, but also named כורש. Coresh. כורש Koresh
שמלך she-melech כשר היה, kasher haya. so explicitly they renamed, he was
named כורש Koresh כשר, kasher כורש Koresh and כשר. kasher, ארתחששתא Artachshasta
על al שם shem מלכותו, malchuto, ומה uma שמו? shemo? דריוש Daryavesh
שמו. shemo. Okay,
so
anyway that solves the כורש Koresh דריוש Daryavesh point. But מכל מקום
קשיא, mi-kol makom kashya, we got a problem. Here, right, when he's
going back, ניסן Nissan is not counted, and the earlier events in
חגי, Chaggai, which were year two, right, by חגי Chaggai you had
something happening well up here in year two, right, and it was
and and there is no
increment. And over there we were saying that תשרי Tishrei was, I'm
sorry, no, from there
תשרי Tishrei occurred between the two, and we were saying the reason
is because ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh is ניסן. Nissan. So you got
a problem. Here the ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh you had to say
was ניסן Nissan to explain why the years didn't increment. Here you
have to
say the ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is תשרי Tishrei to explain why
the years don't increment. How are you going to deal with it?
So just conflating כורש Koresh and דריוש Daryavesh didn't help. It was
just a way of saying כשר היה.
kasher haya. All it could have just said was דריוש Daryavesh כשר
kasher. היה. haya,
It just confuses things. By the way, I once read a book,
it was one of these like almost conspiracy theory books, or maybe
it's better call it like the Dan Brown, what's the name of
his book?
Anyway, basically it explained like חז״ל's Chazal chronology and why they make
sometimes these wild claims like this, conflating דריוש Daryavesh with כורש Koresh
and the whole thing. Anyway, he claimed that it was all done
because they wanted to hide
the implications of the prophecy of Daniel. So since Daniel, you know,
had this prophecy of the אחרית הימים, acharit hayamim, you know, קץ
הימים, ketz hayamim, so they wanted to obfuscate exactly how to count
the years so that it would make it that you couldn't figure
out exactly when משיח Mashiach was going to come. And then he
cracked the code and he was going to tell you when משיח
Mashiach was going to come. I actually read a book like this
once.
Yes, anyway, I do want to say that, yeah, go ahead ask
the question. If you take a look by the way, the בעל
המאור Ba'al HaMaor and the ראשונים, Rishonim, there's an extensive discussion of
trying to make any type of sense out of this גמרא. Gemara.
Let me just sort of show you very quickly here. Here, you
see
this
בעל המאור, Ba'al HaMaor, right, you
see how much... anyway, he's trying to figure out how to make
any logical sense out of the גמרא's Gemara flow. Yeah.
Just from the, for what it's worth from the history teacher point
of view, the Babylonians counted their new, their kingly years from ניסן.
Nissan. Oh they did? So, and I don't know if the Persians
changed that or not, but it's possible a part of the issue,
right, כורש Koresh is the first king who comes in, he defeats
the Babylonians. Uh-huh. So you could still be using the Babylonian system
on some level. Interesting. Babylonian system...
But but we said it was תשרי Tishrei when we were dealing
with ארתחששתא, Artachshasta, which was the earliest, right of that... Well, so
that was תשרי. Tishrei. But you're saying the Babylonian kings were doing
ניסן. Nissan.
Well the Babylonian kings had like the accession year, the year they
came to the throne, but and then they started counting year one
from ניסן. Nissan. Oh, so it's like year zero is the accession,
and year one is ניסן Nissan in the previous king's year.
Okay, so
maybe if you can find out for us when the Persian... I'll
look for it.
That would be very interesting to make things work. To make things
more confusing, כורש Koresh was not only king of Persia, he was
also king of Babylon, but he was king of kings of Persia
for twenty years before he became king of Babylon.
Okay, so moving on.
Right, can we find out the answer?
Okay, keep where we are right now?
Where we are right now is we have said based on the
פסוקים psukim by ארתחששתא Artachshasta
and
נחמיה Nechemia that תשרי Tishrei was the ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah for
נחמיה Nechemia we learned out that תשרי Tishrei was the ראש השנה,
Rosh Hashanah, okay, because of the way it didn't increment at ניסן,
Nissan, the lack of incrementing at ניסן Nissan showed us that it
was תשרי. Tishrei. Then we have the problem that here, right by
from חגי, Chaggai,
it shows us that it does not increment at תשרי. Tishrei. Since
it does not increment at תשרי, Tishrei, that shows us that ניסן
Nissan is the ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. That's what we said, and
therefore we said he was a מלך כשר. Melech Kasher. Okay? Okay,
but
that goes... so that was a special exception. But then here, right
from later in נחמיה, Nechemia,
we find out that it did not increment at ניסן, Nissan, right?
For it didn't increment at ניסן. Nissan. So if it didn't increment
at ניסן, Nissan, then תשרי Tishrei is the ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah,
which makes sense that we're saying it's תשרי, Tishrei, but what about
saying that he was a מלך כשר? Melech Kasher? Okay, this is
all by דריוש. Daryavesh. It could... there was no need to introduce
כורש, Koresh, this is all said by דריוש. Daryavesh. So what's the
גמרא's Gemara answer? So the גמרא Gemara says, מכל מקום קשיא, mi-kol
makom kashya, so we've got a problem. גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבי
יצחק לא קשיא כאן קודם שהחמיץ כאן אחר שהחמיץ. Amar Rabbi Yitzchak
lo kashya, kan kodem she-hichmitz kan achar she-hichmitz.
No,
he started off as a good king, and then he soured. He
became a bad king. By the way, the whole
idea that חמץ chametz
represents יצר הרע yetzer hara and the bad, right.
So they changed the calendar?
They changed it back. Here he was a good guy, so they
were counting from ניסן. Nissan. By the time it got to year
seven, although he's still, I don't know, helping people get back to
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or whatever, anyway, he's not as wonderful as
he used to be, so therefore he's a little bit the wine
is sort of a little vinegary, so we're back to counting him
from תשרי. Tishrei. Okay, so מתקיף לה רב כהנא, Matkif lah Rav
Kahana, so רב כהנא Rav Kahana said,
we'll just do one more line, וממי החמיץ, u'mimi hichmitz, who says
he soured? והכתיב, Ve'hachtiv,
and the פסוק pasuk says that when עזרא Ezra was going back,
here's what Artaxerxes said to him: ומה חשחן, u'mah chashchan, what do
you desire, ומה בני תורין ודכרין ואימרין, u'mah bnei torin ve'dichrin ve'imrin,
whether
it's pigeons or rams or sheep, לעלוון לאלה שמיא, la'alvan l'Eloah shemaya,
to give up to the God of heaven, חנטין מלח חמר
ומשח, chantin melach chamar u'meshach, salt and wine and
oil, כמאמר כהניא די בירושלם, kemamar kahanya di b'Yerushalem,
whatever the כהניא kahanya say in Jerusalem that they want to, you
know, that they need to offer up in their sacrifices, להוא מתיהב
להם יום ביום, leheve mityahiv lahem yom b'yom,
it should be given like from the king's treasury on a daily
basis, ודלא שלו, u'd'la shalu, without them even asking, so you should
provide to them all these needs of the sacrifices from my treasury.
So how could you say he was a bad guy? Look what
he's doing, he's providing funds for the temple... for the temple. So
אמר ליה רב יצחק, Amar lei Rav Yitzchak, so רב יצחק Rav
Yitzchak said back to him, רבי, Rabbi, my master, who was this?
רב כהנא. Rav Kahana. מתונך, Matuncha, right, like the, so מתונך matuncha
is a funny idiomatic expression, it means like from what you're carrying.
The very proof that you give, you have your answer. What does
the end of the פסוק pasuk say? די להוון מהקרבין ניחוחין לאלה
שמיא, di lehevon mehakarvin nichochin l'Eloah shemaya, that they should bring them
as a pleasing aroma to the God of heaven, ומצלין לחיי מלכא
ובנוהי, u'matzlin l'chayei malka u'vnohei, and pray for the life of the
king and for his sons. So therefore, yeah, it's all self-interest. He's
not such a good guy. We should just have so many people
that are doing things like that, that are self-interest and making very
large contributions, and we'll all be very happy, which is what the
גמרא Gemara will discuss tomorrow, since when is doing something like that
not being a good guy.
All right, now I
understand.